Так. Давайте начнём... Добрый вечер, приветствую вас на GV311.
Это первая, а если точнее - вводная неделя. Меня зовут Тони Трэверс,
я профессор на факультете Государственного управления, ответственный за курс GV311.
Пожалуй, перед началом стоит объяснить несколько вещей. У нас здесь стоят
камеры, которые позволят нам записать этот курс в более высоком качестве
по сравнению с тем, что мы имеем для других лекций.
И затем мы это смонтируем и выложим. Так что вы при желании можете
задавать вопросы, их мы тоже заснимем.
Вы также сможете найти эти лекции в Интернете и в...
т.е. просто в Интернете, и посмотреть их записи через некоторое время
после лекций.
Также в прошлом году мы разрешили посещать лекции людям не из университета,
и я заметил, что сегодня несколько таких людей здесь присутствуют.
А теперь не могли бы ребята с курса GV311 поднять руки,
чтобы не беспокоить остальных. Ага.
Хорошо...достаточно. Сейчас просто скажите свои имена
Это наша первая встреча
classes, will also then have a sense of who you are as well.
С ним вы увидитесь в пятницу.
Возможно, вы с ним уже знакомы.
Именааа
Имяяя
Продолжим (Хорошо) (Прекрасно)
what I want to do this week, anyways, just to introduce the course. This is like a
way of explaining what's going to be in the course over the coming...
Yes, sorry?
Yes, is that...my hope that's not a problem. And no, they will be every week, not just
this week. And that means you can watch them again.
We've got...I say it, embarrass my colleagues, slightly higher production
values than on the lecture capture, I hope.
Certainly it was the last year.
Anyway, what I want to do this week is simply to introduce the course. I'm very happy
if you want to ask a question or one or two points, and what I'm going to say,
well, pause where you could, join in,
make a comment, whatever. But I just want to go through what will be in the course
over the next 19 weeks. We've got 19 weeks straight - mixture of...I'll be doing
some of these lectures, we've got guest lectures for most of the other weeks,
and then we'll have a revision slot at the beginning of the summer term.
The purpose of the course is to provide an analytical understanding of
the following things, aspects of the principles that underpin
British government and politics;
political parties, elections and representation;
the origins and operations of the institutions of British government -
any of these you will doubtless of...studied before, but we will take out of it
further, I hope. Some modern historical developments. How - you'll see I'll go
through this in a bit more detail in a minute - how the institutions of
government evolved. We'll be looking at the Judiciary and the court system;
the policy-making process; public finance, including taxation and expenditure;
and, of course, criticisms of all the above and at proposals for reform.
So that's very broadly what the lectures will be covering. Some two lectures will
cover some of these topics, one in other cases. There are things I haven't listed here,
some other themes. We'll be looking at party politics, Professor Patrick Dunleavy.
We will do this: the decline of mass party memberships and
Britain's move to a multi-party system - just before Christmas. And then the role of
the media - looking at the traditional media vs. the new media and their
impact within British politics. Also at ownership and regulation, their impacts
on political life. We'll have a couple of weeks on accountability and financial
responsibility looking at Select Committees, Parliament's more general role
in scrutinizing the Executive, and at possible roles and
improvements of this system. And then last but not least...well, actually, not quite
last...nearly last but not least - British government's relations with Europe.
We can't live without relationship that Britain appears to have
with Europe, and also at the spectrum from the federalism that
some EU countries appear to own versus the threat of withdrawal, which is Britain's
counter to that. And in fact beyond this because it seemed to be an appropriate thing.
The last lecture of next term, that is just in march, we will look at
the British general elections' past, because if you think about it that
lecture will run in March, just before the general election.
We have Professor Vernon Bogdanor, the great
constitutional expert, will come and talk to us about that in March. So that will be
a good lecture to end the series with. What I want to do this
evening is just to run through a number of these things one by one.
I'd be very happy if you want to, you know, ask a question,
join in, don't feel you have to, and, of course, some of these issues will be
picked up in classes and in more detail in the weeks ahead, so this is very much
an attempt to encapsulate everything that will be seen in the coming weeks.
So, I want this week to introduce a number of themes that we'll meet
in the weeks ahead.
British constitution or the lack of it, Parliament and the Executive, the Civil Service,
the Welfare State, Human Rights and British variants on Human Rights,
local government and centralization, devolution which has been obviously
a very big and hugely important issue recently.
You know what's interesting about the whole Scottish referendum debate,
which also a bit more in a moment, is that rather in the way
the economic crisis back in 2008 had the effect, as far as I could see,
of a mass public education in economics and economic theory
very quickly,
the Scottish referendum had, I think, an analogous effect in terms of teaching people
about the British constitution, or more to the point, about the lack of
a written constitution and, indeed, about the begging questions about the
federal nature of Britain. In a country that isn't a federal country, if that
doesn't sound too complicated. I mean, you know. Back to the number of serious
questions which we can look at in the coming weeks. And then, of course,
very briefly I want to turn to Britain and Europe. This is not everything you'll be doing
in the weeks ahead, just a taste of, really.
So if I can just begin with the Constitution, and as I'm sure you're all
aware Britain has a long evolved system of government and politics, I should have
added these slides as all others will be made available to your on Moodle,
so don't feel you have to write them all down, should you wish to.
A long evolved...a system of government and politics with
no written Constitution. We don't have a formal written Constitution.
Very few countries...of which this is true.
Notably, New Zealand and Israel, it's also true of them. But of course we do have
a large number of ad hoc, we have legislation, judicial precedents in the courts,
so it isn't as if there aren't constitutional principles underlying the way
Britain governs itself, but we do not have a codified Constitution.
And, of course, there are a number of commentators - actually,
a very large number,
many based within the school - who believe we should have a written Constitution in the UK.
We also have a series of institutions which have evolved out of antiquity.
Most obviously - the head of state,
the monarchy. Unusual...not unique in Europe by any means, but a head of state
who is a monarch, a system that has been handed down over,
well then you're where you start, over a thousand years and, of course,
a very powerful
monarchical based head of state which has remained its popularity.
Partly because, of course, it is cut off from formal power - doesn't mean it doesn't have
an influence, but cut off from formal governmental power allowing it
most of the time to remain above formal government,
and therefore has none of the disadvantages of the unpopularity
that politicians can court.
We also have a second chamber - the House of Lords,
what in other countries might be a Senate, which itself is constituted in
a very unusual way.
It has its origins like the monarchy...back in the mists of time;
has its origins in the aristocracy, in a particular form of...government
that involved in Britain getting on for a thousand years ago, but where today...
what is left the House of Lords does look unusual by international standards.
So it's a legislative chamber.
It can...legislation goes through the House of Lords as well as the House of Commons,
but in doing so there are checks written into the House of Lords,
for example, it can't vote on money bills and it can only delay bills, it cannot
permanently vote them down. The constitution of the Lords is remarkable
in the sense that it's now an extraordinary mixture of the hereditary
peers, who until the nineteen fifties were the only ones, so people were only in by birth,
and now have been added to them life-peers in very large number -
it's over a thousand of them in total now. But the remaining 92 hereditary peers -
think about this - when one of their...they were left after some reforms
Labour government pushed through between 1997 and 2010. And for the remaining hereditaries,
of course, they sit in party groups, and when the very small groups -
liberal democrats and labor - when one of their members dies then there's a by-election
for the remaining ones to choose another one who must be a hereditary peer.
So, you know, by the great standards of global democracy this is unusual, I think
we can agree, but it's the way the House of Lords operates.
That's our second chamber and in many ways - I don't want to be over critical of it,
because in many ways it has a distance, it's not elected,
therefore it has a bit of distance and can occasionally discuss issues that
the Commons find too hard to discuss.
So there's been a debate in the House of Lords recently about a bill
concerning assisted dying which, I think, is the kind of bill only the Lord's
would really try with that degree of seriousness to look at,
as the Commons find it too difficult.
So an extraordinary second chamber, because we have no formal separation of
powers in this country between the Legislature and the Executive.
Indeed, the Executive - Prime Minister and the Cabinet are derived from
the Legislature.
This is not the way it's done in many countries that have a formal separation
between these things, between these two parts of the state. And, of course, until very recently
the Judiciary were also appointed by the Executive will be it in
a slightly complicated way that has been reformed. We'll hear more about that from
Professor Conor Gearty later this term or early next term soon.
And as I hinted a moment ago, on top of all of this
inherited and evolved governmental arrangement - took a thousand years of it -
we now have Scotland and Wales, and I'll say a bit more about this in a moment,
operating as if they were fed parts of the federal system. So Scotland now
in many ways and soon will have the powers of an American state or a German land,
and yet it's actually exists purely at the whim of the House of Commons,
and it will be possible for Parliament to stop Scottish devolution tomorrow.
They would do that it would be impossible, but nevertheless we
have an increasingly federal system of government in a country without the Constitution,
which isn't any way a federal country, we're a unitary state.
There we have some pictures just to light relief at this point and two aspects,
here is a very glorious picture there of the Queen at the State Opening of Parliament.
This brings together the House of Lords, all those peers in there Herman,
and the Queen, and Prince Philip sitting on that splendid gold throne.
This is the House of Lords,
was not bombed between 1939 - 1945, while the House of Commons was.
And so this looks as it was built in the 19th century. This is a very grand event when
the Queen sits on the throne and reads the government's legislation out.
It's amazing, it is lucky, I suppose, that she doesn't have to show emotion,
because she read it out whoever's in government, whatever the legislation is - straight.
And this, of course, is the Prime Minister and the leader of the Opposition being attending -
and many of you will...certainly, you've seen this
if you live in Britain, will know that the House of Commons is summoned each year
to come to stand at the bar in the House of Lords, bar is not a bar.
It is a bar of that kind, where Black Rod goes to the Commons and invites
the House of Commons to attend the Lords and there
listen to the Queen's speech, the government speech really, and get this
extraordinary picture of the Prime Minister and the leader of the Opposition
attempting to make small talk to each other, and the Liberal Democrat leader
who is actually in the Government, of course, at the moment, just behind doing the same
with Harriet Harman, the Labor deputy leader.
So this sort of brings together the Queen...
this is the day in the year when...all of this sort of process comes
together, because it's these people really - the House of Commons - who have
the power and all of this is to varying degrees less powerful but parts of the system.
Now, in Martin Loughlin, Professor Loughlin it will be speaking later this term.
He wrote a book, a very short guide, a very useful book: this short guide to the British
constitution published very recently in which he said it might be the case that
"the British way of muddling through is best suited to the challenges ahead".
It's the classic argument for muddling through the British constitution.
Lots of people in the British governmental system like it.
"This, though, will never satisfy constitutional modernizers",
of whom were also a large number.
"If Britain is a democracy in which power is exercised in the name of the people,
can the crown still offer an adequate symbol of state?
This is precisely the question which is now to be tested in a referendum" - this
was written before the referendum - "on independence for Scotland
scheduled for autumn 2014.
The Treaty of Lisbon of 2009, it might be noted, requires the EU
to respect the 'constitutional identity' of its member states. But do the British
still possess the confidence to specify that identity?" It's a good question and
it was backed, I think, by the Scottish referendum. I think it did back that question.
We'll hear more about that in the weeks and months ahead, I am sure.
So I think this backs the challenge - we don't have to answer this today,
I just thought some...good sort of think about this: "Should Britain move to
a written constitution, make its remaining unelected State offices
fully democratic" - if you think about that, that's quite radical in the context of
what was up there just now -
"and, more importantly, creating a 'constitutional identity' for the country?"
And "has the Scottish referendum and the outcome of that made this more urgent?"
So just pause on that thought. Talk more about this with Martin Loughlin and others
in the weeks ahead. Feel free if you want to chip in, the same thing about this at any point.
Now, moving on to Parliament and the Executive. "As government has become
bigger and more complex"...
Sorry, a bigger and more complex activity - with my note - "and prime ministers have
become more 'presidential', Parliament has, arguably, become less important".
We'll hear from Professor George Jones about this. He's written
a book about prime ministers and, I think, that's his view very broadly,
but for him to say that. And certainly for any of you who've watched or will now watch
British politics, you'll see that the media concentrate relentlessly on David Cameron,
the Prime Minister, Ed Miliband, the Leader of the Opposition, Nick Clegg,
the Leader of the Liberal Democrats, much in view this week at the Lib Dem's Conference
in Glasgow, and, of course, on Alex Salmond, the Scottish First Minister,
and ever more Sir Boris Johnson, the Mayor of London, our Mayor of London here,
in the fair capital.
And these people do get an extraordinary amount of coverage and publicity
compared with many other parliamentarians in need other parts of
the political system.
Britain has a very nationalized...national media which reinforces this.
Members of Parliament, of the whom there are six hundred and fifty - a large number
by international standards - have to spend more and more time with their
constituents' problems. This is an element of something I'm going to talk about in a moment.
Britain is a centralized country, that's more power has been
drawn to the center.
It's often the case that constituents - that's any of us, who live in the
constituency and we all do within the UK - have to go more often and nod to their
members of Parliament.
If, for example, they've got a problem...if you had a problem with a visa or with your housing,
then go to the MPs. And that means members of parliament now have
huge amounts of constituency work to do, they hold surgeries. And this means that
as they get more power, local government has declined,
I'll say a bit more about that in a moment.
Leaving members of Parliament looking more and more locally at their constituents
while these cabinet ministers, Prime Minister leave the Opposition,
Prime Minister's Question Time are what most people see as politics.
That, I think, backs the interesting question of whether this has something to do
with the often discussed disconnect between most people's lives and politics.
Politics, as seen only on the television, is clearly disconnected.
It's more like a film in some ways than a real thing.
If you know...if you were living in Switzerland with cantons and very local politics,
you might well see things differently. However, and it is quite a significant however,
more recently Select Committees, which are subgroups of the House of Commons,
Committees which have a membership...which reflects the membership of the House of
Commons by party and have committee chairs who also reflect the balance of
the whole House of Commons - so you get a number of Labor chairs even though
the Labour Party's in opposition.
They have undoubtedly been able to provide Parliament with teeth.
If you look on the excellent no-hard-to-find Parliament website, just a wonderful
archive of Select Committee's hearings, you will see a number of Select Committees
digging their teeth into public officials who, they think, have not done the right thing,
broadcasters who they...you might say it's a bit sort of
overtheatrical sometimes, but it undoubtedly has been...has seen a rise of the Select Committee
and, with it, their chairs as public figures.
And many Select Committee chairs these days are more visible in public life than junior ministers.
And that is a big change. Here's an example. That's what most people would
think of as politics - Prime Minister's Question Time,
soundbite on the nine o'clock news. Here we've got David Cameron, looks as if
he's having fun at the Labour Party's expenses - he often does.
There they all sit looking rather glum over there:
Sadiq Khan, Alan Johnson, Ed Miliband and Harriet Harman.
This is a very typical tableau and you can see it the other way around
some of the time, obviously. But here, now,
even if know who this one...this is Mrs. Hodge. Anybody know Mrs. Hodge?
She's the chair...Mrs. Hodge...Yes, you?
MP for Barking, very good, well done. Now...quite a lot of people
know Mrs. Hodge. And Mrs. Hodges is chair of the Public Accounts Committee.
She's a Labour MP. This is the most powerful Select Committee in the House of Commons.
It is backed up by the National Audit Office which is
a proper Department, which is then parliamentary institution, not a
government institution. And Mrs. Hodge has really made a real name for herself
in holding public servants, particularly those who spend large amounts of public money,
to account. And again, National Audit Office reports and
Public Accounts Committee reports are a wonderful source, along with the House of Commons
library notes, if you really want something that's a good source for essays.
And they're a great source of information about contemporary politics.
and I think Mrs. Hodge, but other Select Committee chairs as well
have done exactly the same thing and retiree, who chairs the Treasury Select Committee,
is a conservative, John Whittingdale at the Media Select Committee, Keith Vaz - the
Home Affairs Committee. You'll see all of them now holding the Government
to account in a way that wasn't true
anything like is true in the past, and that's partly because Select Committee chairs
and members are now elected by MPs themselves. They're not simply
appointed by their own parties' authorities and whips.
Now, the influence of Select Committee, this is just a
quote from a book, sort of book, by Meg Russell and another...
published in 2011 which says: "Recent years have been characterised by scepticism -
sometimes verging on cynicism - about the effectiveness of the British House of Commons.
Particularly during the time of large government majorities following
the 1997 and 2001 elections, MPs came to be characterised as 'poodles'",
there's a viewer long memories, you remember, MPs...Labour MPs, at the time it was
popularly imagined...Had pages that told them what to do,
and there was a lot of stuff in the media about this at the time.
"Doubt was expressed about the extent to which the Commons could have a genuine impact on
government policy. And this was reinforced by the fact that during Tony Blair's premiership
the Government was defeated only four times in the House of Commons.
However  - point I was making a moment ago - Select Committees are taken
increasingly seriously by government, and have become an established and respected
part of the system".
So, in the unwritten British constitutional arrangements,
here we have a check and a balance really,
the evolution of a new check and balance on the relatively powerful Executive.
And we'll hear more about this in a couple of lectures next term, including from
Mrs. Hodge's Deputy - he's a conservative who will be giving a lecture next term.
Now, the challenge here, it seems to me, is "should Parliament be given greater
powers to act as a 'check' on the Executive, for example, by increased
support for the Opposition?" The Opposition...and when you are in
government you've got whole of the Civil Service working for you. In Opposition
you've got a little bit of money which is made available from public
purse to support a tiny research team, but that's about it
and anything you can raise privately. So the Government has much more capacity.
So more support, perhaps, for the Opposition, more for Committees -
though Mrs. Hodge's Committee, the PAC, has the National Audit Office behind it,
other Select Committees have one or two advisors and some Clark, who are very good,
but it's not exactly like congressional committees in the United States
which have big teams supporting their members in a way that would be
unthinkable in the historically slightly more relaxed House of Commons.
Should individual MPs have more support?
They now have enormous local post bags and constituency work, and the more
they have of that, less support they got - less support...in relation to
what they need - the less time they have to spend doing that other job,
because their job is to be a representative in Parliament, but they are there,
in Parliament, just as much to be in Parliament as to be back in the constituency.
They tend to spend about half the week in each.
So, you know, should there be greater powers to act as a check on the Executive
in this rather centralized constitution-free system?
The Civil Service. You'll be hearing from Professor Kate Jenkins, who's sitting here,
about the Civil Service in a few weeks time.
"Britain has developed a large, politically independent civil service"...
this is one of the first places in the world to do this, to move away from cronyism and
appointing people's friends to having entry exams and appointment by merit
to run the business of government. In this system - I think it's fair to say
until very recently, in the still a struggle about this - "'Generalised' competence has been prized
over professional skills". So, accountants and economist, for example,
not very highly treasured in government traditionally,
were as those with a rounded understanding of the world, with general skills,
who can move one department to another much more prized.
Though, in fairness to the Civil Service,
it has been struggling in recent years with how to balance getting more of these experts in
without losing the generalized skills and in fairness there is a need, I think, for a balance.
"Cabinet ministers have increasingly appointed 'SPADs' - 'special advisors'.
Many of you may have met special advisors. They are an interesting breed
that allows ministers to bring people into the Department
and then have them in their outer office,
you know, as a sort of direct political contact, working with the civil servants
who are still non-political, of course, delivering the government's objectives,
but in a non-political way, but with these special advisors in the outer office.
Now, sometimes these relationships work really-really well,
and sometimes they work really-really badly, depending on how sensitive the special advisors are
and how much the minute civil servants feel their world is being intruded on
by these special advisors.
"Some ministers would like to move towards having senior officials who are appointed by the Government of the day".
And, indeed, it's fascinating. There was a story in The Financial Times
this morning,
pointing out how Michael Gove, who used to be the Education Secretary
and now has a new role in the Government as the Leader of the House...
Chief Whip, sorry. I've got him confusing with William Hague. Chief Whip, thank you.
Chief Whip.
He has started to attend the weekly meetings of the Permanent Secretaries.
Now, this is a very big and unusual step,
not much liked by the civil servants. Thank you for the Chief...He's indeed the Chief Whip.
And that seems somebody who is the Government's business manager.
Attending the meetings of civil servants is a big and unusual change to have occurred.
Now, "the civil service can be seen as lacking in management, financial and other expertise",
but in fairness to it,
its skills as a permanent government, or permanent deliverer of government,
and its lack of political bias are clearly enormously important to the operation
of the state, and there are trade-offs here.
This is the head of the... it's the Cabinet's Office...Cabinet Secretary
Sir Jeremy Heywood, stepping out of a car - lots of pictures of him on the Internet
stepping out of the car for some reason -
going into Downing Street, it would appear. And this, of course, here, is
the fictitious account of life inside government, if any of you have ever seen
"The thick of it".
I thought of playing a clip, but I couldn't find one
that I could respectably play.
So I didn't, but you can find them. There was a particularly good one,
when I was looking for this photograph, of 'life imitating art' on the BBC website.
It's a BBC clip on YouTube, available through YouTube, which shows
how things that happened in "The thick of it" then happened in real life soon after.
So...and, of course, "The Thick of it", although having Doctor Who
in the front of the picture as well to make it seem
more odd-looking,
"The Thick of it", although, of course, a satirical take on government.
I think you'd find very few people in government who didn't think it had a vestige,
a tiny element of certain elements of the way both the previous Labour Government
and then the current Conservative Lib Dem coalition operate.
Perhaps, in different ways. This was a bit more 'shouty', and the early days of
"The Thick of it" under the coalition were a bit more 'new age', but there was a definite...
I'm not saying you should watch it to learn British government and politics,
but I'm not saying you shouldn't watch either. Now, just to take on this issue
from the Institute for Public Policy Research who published a long report on
this last year, made recommendations for reform. And I'm not saying he's aright,
there're just examples of what a commentator, an external commentator, might say.
You know that we should "give the prime minister the power to appoint permanent secretaries,
but without politicising the civil service". You can see in that comment
there is a paradox, really. Having...your obviously permanent secretaries
whom the Government of the day wants to work with, but if they're appointed by the Government,
there is a risk of politicization. "Providing secretaries of state and ministers
who run their own departments with an extended office of
ministerial staff that they personally appoint" - we're in the same territory here -
"and who work directly on their behalf in the department". And what you can see here
is the tension between the traditional British way of doing things
and a sort of cabin air, an american-style government, of a kind that
looks fine works right therem, but it's very different from
the traditions that Britain has operated with the independent Civil Service,
the Executive taken out of the Legislature.
They propose "strengthening the role of the head of the civil service to hold
permanent secretaries to account". The current head of the civil service,
who is not Sir Jeremy Heywood, as recently as just about to step down,
gave a very interesting speech at the Institute for Government,
which is available on their website, about his efforts to help
to hold secretaries to account, if you want to follow that up.
The IPPR suggested "introducing fixed-term, four-year contracts
for new permanent secretaries" -
these are the people at the top of each department, I should've added.
"Strengthening the external accountability of civil servants in key operational roles" -
that's what Mrs. Hodge has been doing. And then, of course, "enabling the civil service
to better support opposition parties - again controversial - by allowing officials
to be seconded into opposition parties to help them with policy development".
So all of these ideas are perfectly sensible, but once you say them
they do tend to,
I think, infringe the way many traditional civil servants and, indeed, non-traditional,
but extensible servants would imagine their world working,
but they may be things that would improve the operation of government
and, indeed, the civil service.
So the challenge here, it seems to me, is: "Has the time come to move to
a politically-appointed civil service of people with professional expertise?"
It'd be a very different kind of civil service. Possibly better, possibly not.
Something we can talk about in the weeks ahead.
The Welfare State. We all know about Britain's Welfare State,
many European step countries and, indeed, others have either an extent
or developing Welfare State.
"Britain has developed a very large set of welfare services, - which we call 'Welfare State' -,
in the years since 1945". The development of a National Health Service,
education for all, social housing,
a range of services where there's a social element in the provision.
This 'Welfare State' now appears to face a number of challenges,
not the least of which is: "Will the public pay the taxes sufficient to fund
a full welfare state?"
Any of you watching the party conferences recently, you will see this debate
subliminally there all the time. Famously, Leader of the Opposition,
you remember this, neglected to talk about the deficit,
Britain's large deficit, but the Conservatives have been criticized subsequently
for promising tax cuts the time when Britain is indeed still running
a very large deficit.
The difficulty for all parties is that they've got themselves into a sort of fixed system,
like a weather system where the taxes...
it appears, they are willing to charge more to make people pay...are less than
the scale of the state that people want. And I'll show you a chart about this in a moment.
Beyond that we are a consumer society, it's a cliche, but you know what we mean,
we want to consume things, people understand their rights and those rights are
a long way away from the ideas that underlay, for example, the National Health Service
back in the forties.
I don't think when the NHS was created an iron better from a great
Labour politician created it, that he or anybody else thought that people would
feel they had the right to demand every new drug that came on the market
or very expensive new drugs. Now, all of us in the room can sympathize with people who feel that
if they are a relative is ill that they should be able to get a new drug
from a system that's free at the point of use, but, clearly, there isn't
limitless money and consumer attitudes to what we consume may have made
running the Welfare State more difficult than it once was.
Some households, it has been argued, have become 'dependent' on the state.
If you look at the scale of what the Beveridge report, the great 1942 report,
that proposed the creation of Welfare State,
the minimal level of unemployment pay and other benefits that it proposed, compared with
the scale of welfare today, as of today, the welfare budget, pensions and
all others cost more than 200 billion pounds in the United Kingdom.
That is a very significant sum of money for a 1.5 trillion, so 1600 billion, economy.
So it's 200 out of 1600. And there are those who believe that
households in some cases have become 'dependent' on the state. And, of course,
over-all the state...the whole of the Welfare State has grown substantially,
not only social security, but the National Health Service, schools, housing
and more besides.
Now, this is a classic 1940s style cartoon
showing Beveridge attempting to slay the five great evils that he saw lying...
It's interesting how creative British public servants were
during the Second World War, coming up with a series of reports and proposals for legislation
to change the way the country ran, partly because of the cooperation
and nationalization that have gone on during that very Second World War.
So: Want, Ignorance, Disease, Squalor, Idleness - these great evils
that were to be slayed by the Welfare State.
More recently the current Secretary of State, Iain Duncan Smith, you'll see him in the news,
is trying to introduce a radical new reform to bring many of the welfare benefits,
other than pensions, together into a universal credit and in attempt,
in his view, to reduce dependency - and it's not as if the Labour Party
hasn't brought me support at these, so, you know, reduce dependency, but also
to remove perverse incentives, kind of incentives that have existed where
people who receive benefits find that as they earn money and come off benefits
they become worse off.
So, in fairness to Iain Duncan Smith the objective is clearly one that
many people might support,
but crucially is very difficult to introduce because of the computer systems and
moving from one system to another and the changes in treatment of
individuals as that happens. In a book written by another LSE professor,
not certainly one who's speaking in this course, but one of his books will be
on the reading list, called "Understanding the Finance of Welfare" Howard Glennerster
has written. This is a very interesting up some, it seems to me, of the problem
that the free at the point of delivery Welfare State offers any society.
"Users of public services seem increasingly dissatisfied,
despite the fact that the quality of services has improved since 1950.
The level of consumer expectations seems to be rising faster. Discontent may be
put down to a malevolent press or professions who continuously talk of
'crisis' as a way of gaining more resources from the Chancellor.
The NHS, of course, has been in 'crisis'
ever since it was created", - and, indeed, it's certainly in the square bracket,
certainly as today,
according to the media this morning. "However, there is a more structural explanation
for this continuing dilemma. Claus Offe, a German Marxist sociologist,
comes closest to capturing it, although there is
an equivalent New Right explanation. In a pure market economy the price mechanism
manages individuals' expectations. They may desire a Mercedes or
a holiday in the Bahamas but they know their capacity to afford such luxuries
is determined by their own worth in the labor market. They do not blame the government.
In health and education, where no prices is charged,
expectations are not managed downwards by the market. Supply and demand have to be managed
by the political process. [We need to consider] the way in which scarce resources
are managed and allocated in a non-market system. The dilemmas should not
blind us to the fact that all scarce resources have to be rationed".
And if you look at an institution that many of you who live in Britain
will know - NICE,
which is the National Institute for Clinical Excellence, I think it's changed
its name, but near enough NICE,
they have had the problem for some years now trying to ration the use of drugs,
prescribed drugs in the NHS. And once you start talking about rationing,
many politicians run away, don't like to talk about rationing.
But if you think about it,
the NHS has to ration health resources. There isn't a limitless
supply of doctors, nurses and pharmaceuticals.
It is all about rationing, and politics is how that has to be done.
Here's the chart I promised. This is my favorite chart at the moment. This is produced by
the Office for Budget Responsibility, an excellent organization with an excellent website,
which produces independent economic forecasts and measures of
public expenditures. Just wonderful. And the top line there shows public expenditure
as a proportion of GDP in the United Kingdom since 1978-1979,
it's the dark line you can see it at the top there.
the lighter line which is generally
below it is government revenues that tax
take and every time the dark line is
above the light line
there's a deficit in the very very
occasional times when the light line is
above the dark line there's a surplus
so at all times the one who bit the dark
lines above the light line the
government national the national debt is
rising and of course has been rising
substantially the dotted line marks
broadly where we are today just was
slightly this way now
and as you can see and what we face is a
substantial further fall in public
expenditure as a proportion of GDP up to
the point the deficit is eradicated
but more interesting that is the if you
look at the smooth average of the lower
line the government receipts line from
1992 today
it's never got above thirty eight
percent of gdp
so no government in
united kingdom has put taxes up about
thirty-eight percent of GDP ever in any
year since 1990
that's nearly quarter of a century if
you listen to the narrative of politics
no desire to put taxes up on most people
site designed to put them up on the rich
but not on everybody else
the rich sadly are not large enough in
number to change that line much there
for Britain has stalled attractive so
we're not unique in this but Britain is
now trapped in the position of wanting
to have in effect but it simply Sweden
or Frances public sector with America's
taxes and that's what this chart shows
we want a big estate and what then
some politicians are able to convince us
to pay and that is a real problem
because within the expenditure line
health and welfare is growing so
everything else is having to shrink
defense shrunk local government
shrinking police and fire shrinking big
issues will come back to those i'll be
talking about that in a few weeks time
so how could the government changed the
welfare state and Institute ensure it
was sustainable just to ration resources
but also that this did not generate
unintended consequences and I think the
only answer to that is to put up taxes
are not advocating putting up taxes i'm
just saying that unless we are to have
much more rationing in the welfare state
we are going to need to put taxes up and
it taxes don't go up as a share of the
economy
then we will see substantially more
rationing the story in The Independent
today the independent newspaper saying
that it may be that the one on one of
the professional organizations saying it
may be necessary to charge people
hospital fees
sorry hotel fees for staying in
hospitals and that will get more debates
of that kind in the coming months and
years
europe this is not quite as random as on
I mean this is with them sort of moving
through the weeks of lectures quickly
here in summary
europe now Europe's been an
extraordinarily potent issue dominating
British government and politics for 30
or 40 years now
Britain joined the UN the seventies had
a referendum in 1975 about whether we
should stay in or not
and of course many of you will be aware
that a number of British politicians and
indeed an entire new insurgent political
party a lobbying hard for Britain
radically to change its relationship
with Europe broadly defined
now what we're going to look at within
this course is both your as an issue of
Rights and the cute part of the
judiciary and the court system but also
Europe as the European Union remembering
of course and this is rarely . really
made in public discourse that of course
the human rights issue and the European
Court of Human Rights is nothing to do
with the EU there listening to the
debate on these things be hard to
differentiate them most of the time now
. professor conjugate he will talk about
the judiciary and rights and the British
approach to rights but in summary the
way
Britain has a . Britain has done is to
adopt as a number of countries have the
many of the elements of the European
Convention on Human Rights they've been
incorporated by convention into our and
other countries legal systems either
through constitutional provision or by
statute we don't have a constitution
after all or through judicial processes
and then the European Court of Human
Rights which is not as I stress part of
the European Union it his cases that are
alleged to contravene the country
the convention the court cases cases are
heard in the UK course in other
countries cause we can in the end be
appealed to the european court of human
rights now
again those of you who watched the news
carefully will know there's a number of
high-profile cases often though not
exclusive
only involving terrorism suspects
not only that and occasionally people
have broken the law have ended up in the
european court of human rights and cause
not in significant aggravation to some
British politicians as a result of that
the conservatives that their party
conference recently proposed to repeal
the Human Rights Act 1998 which was the
law that by which the Labour government
of the time incorporated provisions of
the European Convention into British law
so that's how this was done and instead
to produce a bill of rights
this would be in effect to create
something that sounded a bit more
English a bill of rights and 16 18 and
going back to history and trying to
escape in part from the european
convention on human rights but
particularly actually not that but from
the court
I just thought a cartoon on this
occasion and I like this color I mean
this is see it is such a relief to dicks
the human rights court and get back to
common sense is what the caption is on
this particular cartoon from The Daily
Telegraph last week and clearly that is
the sense that if we you know that among
many politicians are not only in the
conservative party if only we could
control our own
the decisions of not this controller
decisions of the courts would have all
these case with cases were decided by
British judges you get common sense i
think that's the sort of prevailing
feeling now would repealing the Human
Rights Act 1998 really make a difference
unless the UK withdrew from the
convention system under which the
European confirm convention operates ,
Garrity will be speaking to you later on
in the course I think argues not in ddr
give not in the Guardian a few days ago
and and you might want to argue analyzed
you know I think so
it's a moot point we don't have a
different view on this as to whether
it's a good or a bad thing that there is
a European long stop influencing British
law acting as a sort of and an
internationally based appeal court for
perceived or real in justices with in
this country
now people have different views on that
and we'll hear from the about that from
congregating in his lecture local
government local government and
centralization as I said much earlier on
britain's a unitary and not a federal
state with no written constitution this
makes it very easy for national
governments of any party to pass laws
that affect the powers of sub national
government
now interestingly that has led to the
creation of devolved scottish and welsh
and Northern Irish assemblies
but within England and indeed separately
in each of those countries local
government has actually become less
powerful written is a highly centralized
country particularly and then if you
look at the share of taxes and political
control that are held at Westminster for
England separately in Edinburgh
cardiff and north Belfast for the other
three parts of the UK
ninety-five percent of all the taxes in
the United Kingdom are set by the
Chancellor
exchequer if you look at the OECD
statistics beautifully laid out in
fabulous charts
so you can see how Britain compares with
other UK compares with other countries
in oecd you'll find that this is a very
low percentage
indeed and indeed as the other the five
percent which is a local property tax is
frozen and cat
it's really a hundred percent so here we
are in a large mature democracy with a
hundred percent of all the taxes that by
national government very very unusual as
oecd helpfully shows England's had known
to meet devolution even though England
the country of 52 million people
scotland five Wales three northern
ireland one and a half million people
know d evolution within England Labour
government did try a referendum in the
Northeast to introduce devolved regional
government there in 2004
but the powers on offer was so modest
that the North people of the north east
they might be with good reason rejected
it so what we have seen laterally is new
forms of local governance emerging
efforts to sort of get around this city
regional level in other sub - Allah
units that are not quite new government
units but do provide an opportunity for
some more effective operation as an
area-wide of the one local authority
practice and Wilson writing about local
democracy and local government say
there's a vital element of the
constitutional makes the local element
has withered and his danger of
disappearing altogether even more
pessimistic and I was just then the
centralization many services
the circumvention of local government
and the diminution of local politics of
all compounded to foster a democracy
that increasingly north and belittles
all things local which gives excessive
emphasis and national politics going
back to the pictures and some of the
points I made earlier the persistently
low turnout at local elections and the
tendency for them to be used as
indicators of National Party preferences
are symptomatic of this trend
the practice and habits of democracy at
the local level which remains the
foundation of our national democratic
culture are in retreat and in fact this
is quoted in the prep by practicing
Muslim but it's the forward by Sir Simon
Jenkins great columnist in the Guardian
in his forward to that a book
I think that's pretty fair comment but
we can talk about that in the weeks
ahead here the challenges does the
centralization of power in England
weekend local government in ways which
in turn undermine local politics and
thus the basis for the national
political parties and that's a very if
you think about it an interesting
question
all politics is local not my original
idea an American politician said that
all politics is local and the truth is
if local government erodes and inroads
we're with the basis of national
politics be all members of parliament
are selected by local party members
local party members
look to local government many of them
are counselors and without that local
government functioning healthfully how
would the parties survive they're
already shrinking
how would they survive without that
local unit of government so there is a
link between local government and
politics and national politics evolution
and I've touched on this already
stockland whales have been given their
own Parliament and government
this was a radical change and I said it
was a we can discuss we will discuss
further into the course how this
happened is very centralized state the
United Kingdom suddenly after 1997 with
the advent of the Labour government then
dissolving power to Scotland and Wales
number of reasons for this
it had been tried earlier in fact in the
nineteen seventies not and had been
rejected just and we well it's so i
should say was rejected in Wales but not
in Scotland but i was going to explain
when we get there
I didn't want to get really go all the
way back through nineteen nineteen
seventy-nine again
so but there was a threshold i think was
the point there was the threshold at the
time and that's that was very nearly an
issue the other week of course there was
a threshold above which the Scots would
have had to get to trigger the
devolution that was proposed in the late
seventies
so virtually all domestic policy is now
handled by edinburgh and Cardiff
edinburgh and carted now have
extraordinary person indeed Belfast
Northern Irish the Northern Irish
assembly Northern Ireland Assembly has
analogous and significant powers which
given the extraordinary history of
Northern Ireland just shows you how
radically things have changed their that
has been devolution to northern ireland
assembly which is not available within
England and that is a real signal that
our northern ireland has moved on
major taxation powers are to be handed
over to Scotland following the 2014
referendum those of you watching the
referendum within the last few weeks
we've seen golden brown our former prime
minister suddenly appearing as a great
hero of the No campaign would appear to
offer on behalf of the labor
conservative and liberal democrat
parties much greater taxation power for
Scotland power to borrow money welfare
freedom freedom to operate well for part
of the welfare system much more radical
even then the Scots had already been
offered
so what the Scots are going to get is
the thing that was originally refused to
them in the questions on the ballot
paper sort of devo max option as it was
called which will make Scotland in my
view
akin to a federal unit within a federal
state but because we're not a federal
state as i said earlier but the Scots
will have very significant autonomy
including crucially not only budgeting
autonomy but now tax-raising powers as
well
started conservative leader came up with
the most radical suggestion
intriguingly to develop all income
tax to Scotland the whole income tax and
that would make it a very very developed
system indeed and we were still with us
we're now in the process of the
Westminster system having to decide
exactly what it now offers scotland on
the back of this wails of course we'll
ask for something similar Wells is
already been promised tax-raising powers
but you can see that on the belt back of
whatever Scotland is now given wales
which is in a slightly different
situation because it's a less affluent
country in terms of its tax raising
capacity but the world will similarly be
offered at least some form of the local
income tax and other tax raising powers
so how do we create this federal default
system of countries as nations within
the united kingdom when the UK isn't a
federal state and more than that was
about England England is 50 to 60
seconds of in terms of population and
GDP of the United Kingdom
professor John Curtis the great several
logical expert from strathclyde
university
I remember speaking at a lecture in
London about five years ago long before
all this was going on making the point
that the only way for a country united
kingdom which consists of one country
which has 52 million people in it
one with 51 with three and one and one
and a half the anyway that can hold
together is if it's some level
the Scots the Welsh in the Northern
Irish have more power than their numbers
suggest to try to balance hours
the imbalance that would otherwise occur
with England being so dominant an
interesting idea
I credited to him and happy and I
remember that correctly but it's a good
idea
and so in in recent times Scotland
after all has high levels of public
expenditures in England sodas well so
there's Northern Ireland they have more
representation in Parliament of Scotland
and of course their own government as
wales and northern ireland do
perhaps that's an essential condition
for allowing the united kingdom to
continue but that begs the
certain of what happens if you did give
and this is being discussed as we speak
England greater autonomy there are
conservative and other MPs who think
England should have its own Parliament
with its own ministers with the first
minutes in English First Minister
perhaps like the Scottish First Minister
we you know then
then the budget of the English
government will be bigger than the
remaining UK government and that would
be a bit lopsided win it a bit like as
if California were I don't know bigger
than had a bigger budget than the UK US
federal government or something like
that doesn't kind of makes sense if you
sort of think it through
so what will come out of all of this I
suspect though this will happen during
the course of our lectures so this will
be in real time is a another British
constitutional fudge of some kind it'll
be a mixture of some British vote
english votes for some English laws or
parts of that but probably not an
english parliament but we'll see these
debates will be going on in real time
around us a cheery picture here before
the referendum actually of the Prime
Minister meeting the First Minister
about social said the first minister
meets the prime minister would have been
more accurate in which side of the
understanding of the handsome matter of
Scotland behind them
this was at the point where they decided
to hold the referendum and these are two
quotes which I won't read out now
because we're running short while we
were beginning to run towards 615 but
this is really the SNP's arguments
distilled here for Scott them becoming
an independent nation and the UK
government's arguments for maintaining
the partnership better together within
never elected from professor Jim
gallaher about this
who took part in this campaign I think
he was actually involved in a
no personal secret here on the No
campaign but he will give a very
independent view of this I'm sure as he
did when he spoke last year so
fascinating on it for me and if any of
you for me
anybody get voted in this referendum
either way just as a matter of interest
now I'm not Scottish
i was born in wales as it happens but as
a UK voter i found this referendum the
most exciting election in my life more
than general elections and then if any
of you shared that view
so even if you weren't Scottish or
voting in the scottish referendum
it was never the less than a real
electrifying act activity and as the
early mentioned professor Curtis said it
another seminar here a few weeks ago
why was the turnout so high we'll simply
because the result massive 85% turn
ninety seven percent registered votes an
extraordinary and an extraordinary
election and the result mattered and I'm
afraid the implications this is turning
out to lower in other elections because
people think they don't matter that the
tragic the other side of that tragic
coin so challenge was it good or bad for
Scotland and in what ways that it did
not vote for independence this is
something the Scots and the remainder of
the UK
I think we'll debate for a long time to
come they may want to have another go at
it
that's not relaxed possibility out
depends what the UK government now
offers them and how that system works
thereafter will it be like Quebec where
there was a second reference and we'll
whatever comes out of this be good or
bad for England more powerful Scotland
more powerful Wales more powerful
Northern Ireland
what will the English get out of this
the English who are this large majority
you generally don't desert themselves
but who may be about to some extent by
the English do it now
written in Europe as i said earlier know
it know a few more vexed over the long
term
then Britain's relationship with Europe
it's a complex relationship and often a
different one
Britain had an in-out referendum soon
after we joined in nineteen having not
join the European Community originally
then joined late and had a referendum
soon after to decide whether or not we
should stay in the EU euro skepticism
we had a lot more of this from Simon
Hicks next term drives a number of
conservative and you keep politicians as
a significant fringe the Conservative
Party the whole of you keep an insurgent
party within the UK mainstream and to be
fair some labor ones as any one party
and advertising it i'm just saying is
the matter of fact one party that is now
four square pro-eu pro Europe would
broaden it and that's the liberal
democrats they
that's a one they've got a number of
things where they are unique and this is
one of them the lib dems are a
pro-european party labor some way back
across the spectrum the conservative
some way from them and you get well
beyond them on some kind of spectrum
that's fair to all concerned it's hard
not to be aware of the fact that the
United the British media are often
highly critical of the EU and other
European institutions whether or not
they're part of the EU
maybe if you'll be aware of the endless
fabled stories about some you know still
need to have on straight bananas and all
of this nonsense that gets in the media
from time to time and all of that sort
of stuff there's a lot of it but public
opinion is regularly split
actually it's generally in favor it
pushed generally push decision will
generally say that people on balance
would like to stay in the e u-- of
course though we now operate in the
world where the Conservative Party in
particular
and you kept by the Conservatives are
committed but if they win the next
general election outright the election
next year they'd hold an in-out
referendum as to whether UK should stay
there will be it on terms that would
have been renegotiated by david cameron
by the Conservatives in the meantime you
keep just wants an in-out referendum
- I think in fairness to them just to
argue to leave
Labour's position is more nuanced
Liberal Democrats I think they're
discussing whether or not they should
have a referendum or should support the
idea of a referendum because frankly
whether you believe in staying in all
going getting out a referendum could be
seen at least for a while as clearing
the air
so where the are on either side of the
argument you might think that's just
stop the argument for a bit
whether it would or not is another
matter but clearly we may well face a
referendum within the next two years and
what the scottish referendum tells us
three years
what the scottish referendum tells us is
that there are consequences consequences
in terms of the instability or the
perceived instability of the country's
political and financial institutions
whether it's fair or not you could see
from the latter days of the scottish
referendum when it was thought that it
was possible to scotts would vote yes to
leave the UK that you know he suddenly
started hearing about banks thinking of
moving their headquarters and less
investment and all sorts of you know
fires of Hades pouring down if this
happened
now whether it would have been like that
will never neck but all i can say is
that on the basis of that experience
when this debate happens about Brittany
you it's hard not to believe will get
the same kind of it all go to the dogs
or the work won't go to the dogs kind of
debate so it'll be a really I think the
scottish referendum absolutely important
vital in its own right was also
revealing in what it tells us about how
and a referendum on britain's staying in
or leaving the EU might turn out so many
good pictures when you come to look at
Britain Europe
available this is a classic of President
meter on mrs. Thatcher probably looking
the other way to talk to somebody going
cropped like this it simply looks like a
metaphor for everything to do with
Britain's relationships with was not
only Europe also France I'm afraid but
there we are
and it is just one of them it is an
undying issue in British politics with
here to that we have two lectures on
this from Simon Hicks press X next term
now this is what David Cameron thinks
the choice is and he is an interesting
position because he's placed himself
I think that somebody who would want to
vote to stay in the EU but is also the
person whose party includes many people
want to leave it and who has to
negotiate if there is this in out
referendum and he still Prime Minister
with Europe which I have to say doesn't
show that much sign and wanting to make
life easy for the British well let's see
what he said at Bloomberg 18 months ago
a real choice between leaving or being
part of a new settlement in which
Britain shapes and respect the rules of
the single market that is protected by
fair safeguards and free of the spurious
regulation bananas which damages that I
added that obviously damages
Europe's competitiveness choice between
leaving or being part of a new
settlement in which Britain is at the
forefront of collective action on issues
like foreign policy and trade and where
we where we leave the door firmly open
to new members a new settlement subject
to the democratic legitimacy and
accountability of national parliaments
where member states combined inflexible
cooperation respecting national
differences not always trying to
eliminate them in which we approved that
some powers can in fact be returned to
member states the british want to
repatriate powers most other countries
particularly France and Germany want to
do the opposite
in other words a settlement which would
be entirely in keeping with the mission
for an updated European Union i have
described today more flexible more
adaptable more open fit for the
challenges of the modern age and to
those who say a new settlement can't be
negotiated
i would say listen to the views of other
parties in our European countries
arguing for powers to flow back to
European states well I'm not absolutely
sure the core countries are some of the
others might be but of course beyond
this
what's further added since he made this
speech really to the pecan see of this
whole debate is the question of
immigration immigration in unprompted
opinion polling in Britain
Maury does regular one . unprompted has
done it for years unprompted questions
what do you think of the most important
issues in Britain today
number one is immigration the
Conservatives when they were in
opposition and that conservatively done
coalition have brought down or sought to
bring down the level of immigration from
outside the EU but of course within the
EU
there is free movement of labour that's
how it works
free movement of capital and labor and
so as immigration from outside the US
decline immigration from inside the EU
has gone up and this means that from mr
cameron and for other British
politicians it would be so different for
the Labour Party frankly they face the
problem that the EU su is tangled up
with immigration which is a much more
salient and potent issue even the europe
are arguably and so when it comes to
these renegotiations and it's not really
mentioned in this long quote the idea
that you know he says in this speech and
the door firm the open to new members
are not absolutely sure to be the door
firmly open to new members with the
right to move backwards and forwards
across international boundaries but
we'll see
very complicated issue with the cut with
the Prime Minister right at the heart of
it
so the big issues it seems to me with
Europe is what are the issues and
history because history in this that lie
believe beneath Britain strained
relationship with the EU and my tree
negotiation and an in-out referendum
finally sort things out well as I mean
if i can offer a personal view here
no I should be doing this too often I
doubt it will ever be finally in British
Britain's case even if the were
referendum it's hard to believe it would
be finally and this is just one of those
recurring questions which will probably
stay with Britain for a long time to
come
whether or not there is such a
referendum now just finally this is by
no means a lot of a full list but you
know in looking ahead to the coming year
some of the essays that will need to be
written so on
there are so many institutions and other
rock
not all these all institutions in
various ways but all of them are
relevant and are being reformed the
heart of the British constitution
permanently in flux the lib dems are
discussing it and on and off at their
party comes up in glasgow the role of
the monic regularly disgusting as play
showing in the West End about the
imagined early days of King Charles the
third the role of the monarch
permanently under debate
perhaps less so with the current Queen
as head of state but it's always an
issue for some people
House of Lords very much more as an
issue of current debate should it be
reformed think overwhelmingly there's a
belief that should the difficulty is
nobody can think of a an option that
everybody would agree with and therefore
it's hard to do anything
House of Commons number of reforms would
be made to the business practices of the
House of Commons but not much more than
that you know
could it operate on more modern
procedures well yes
the British legislation that legislative
processes which I'm touched on at all
today are complex of there are many
countries we have many more acts of
parliament and we once did
and the process itself has been
regularly criticized for being not only
obscure but often rushed
we now have new processes like the
consideration draft bills and lots of
things going on there
select committees we talked about the
major political parties what we have you
know the
served to party the Labour Party in the
liberal democrats are all in there vary
in their way and if you see this in the
current opinion polls they are all
unpopular at the same time it's very
unusual to have your three traditional
major parties unpopular the same time
normally you get the government and
popular in the opposition's popular well
actually all three are in the polls at
the moment
that's partly because there are
insurgent parties particularly you Kip
but also here in there the greens
so you keep to the right of these three
the Greens to the left of these three
interesting to wonder if they were a
Labour government will find out that
before the end of the academic year just
you know whether the if there were a
Labour government whether the Greens
would become a party a bigger party of
protest if the lib dems didn't fulfill
that protest the pope didn't have that
job at the time manifestos well we'll be
running into manifesto season the
textual analysis and manifestos and what
politics government then do with them
always interesting
lobbyists we've had in the last year
legislation to try to curtail the
activities of lobbyists
there are many like many many lobbyists
out there now and I don't just mean
lobbying company's most big companies
have their own in-house lobbyists
there are many companies that do this
some of you may want to go work in such
companies in years ahead they are an
important element in the political
system and have many interesting people
working in them
elections turn out and voting school has
a week the NRC government department has
initiative running on this and we will
be i should say in the run-up to the
general election doing a lot more many
more activities including a conference
on the general election our March friday
the thirteenth of March
just remember that date friday the 13th
one else next year and
and we will be doing more on opinion
polls &amp; posters there's more opinion
polls at any time in history
London has great access to the opinion
polls &amp; posters
the school has good relations with them
they are an opportunity for his or civil
service
Downing Street in the Treasury all
subject to so near permanent debate
about whether they should change and be
reformed didn't up talk much about
Downing Street today
large books are written by just about
the not only about the day-to-day
workings of Downing Street but some
people about the layout of desks and
doors in Downing Street how these things
matter to the way power is used in the
british political system and the
Treasury the all-powerful Treasury at
the top of the uk's finance ministry and
then finally the sub-national
institutions not by any means last but
not least which we touched on already
including in London with its
extraordinary Merrill system led by
boris johnson recently selected to
become a parliamentary candidate in the
next general election and then of course
London is the British capital of think
tanks those of you might just make a
suggestion
want to meet large numbers of
interesting people in the evenings for
free and debate all sorts of issues
there are dozens of think tanks within
two miles of here all of whom would love
to see you for their events you know the
IPPR Policy Exchange social market
foundation center for social justice
compasses loads and loads of them
I'd avail yourself of them but crucially
they too are a subject worthy of study
in their own right
their influence on politics these days
very important
next week which will be the first
lecture in the series will hear about
the philosophical influences and the
history of ideas from Professor Paul
Kelly and talk about this today at all
this will give us an introduction to the
philosophy and ideas that underpin
British politics government and its
constitutional development
and also looking at some of the recent
in contemporary influences on today's
political leaders
Переведено на Нотабеноиде
http://translate.kursomir.ru/book/134/818
Переводчики: romaraute, annasvetlova